<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ramos on Software</title>
    <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ramos on Software</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 13:23:10 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jcjramos.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The logging triology - ELK Elasticsearch &#43; Logstash &#43; Kibana</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2019-01-08-the-log-triollogy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2019-01-08-the-log-triollogy/</guid>
      <description>One of the side effects of a microservices architecture is that checking logs soon becomes a problem. At the beginning of the process, when you think about containerizing an application, it seems simple and straightforward – you just log to stdout and docker or kubernetes handle it. But then &amp;hellip;
Where is my log ? The number of different services &amp;amp; service instances rapidly explodes and then it becomes really difficult to find a particular log and to troubleshoot the misbehaviour of a micro-service.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More About Helm - Values</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2019-01-04-more-about-helm-values/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2019-01-04-more-about-helm-values/</guid>
      <description>Manage deployments is a import concern when creating a microservices based application, given the typical huge number of services involved and the possible variations you need a way to keep complexity under control. Helm can be a usefull tool, besides been a very cool way to define dependencies ( see this previous post ), Helm introduces an interesting concept called values ( not quite original, but implemented in a nice way ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My favorite BuzzWords for 2018</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-12-21-favorite-buzzwords/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-12-21-favorite-buzzwords/</guid>
      <description>Techies love BuzzWords, every year there is new popular technology or concept that everyone talks about, soon these fall in to oblivion and are replaced by new trends. Not all the Buzzwords referrer to completely useless stuff, some concepts really got past the Buzz part and became really useful parts of our lives, but eventually people got tired to discuss them, or they became too common to be interesting ( I guess Blog was a buzzword a few years ago ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Helm</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-12-19-about-helm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-12-19-about-helm/</guid>
      <description>Microservices are supposed to be small and dedicated, the issue when you move an application to a microservices based architecture is that you quickly get many of them. Dealing with each service individually becomes much easier as they get more “micro”, but deal with the whole bunch can be a nightmare. Look at the example bellow, in the 1st interaction of a typical application it became something like this :</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About not-so-microservices</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-12-17-not-so-microservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-12-17-not-so-microservices/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes, in particular when moving large legacy systems to a microservices architecture you came up with the dilemma, what to do about the not-so-microservices ? these are typically large monolith blocks from a bygone era. Developers are afraid of these, no one want’s to mess with them. But we live in a messy world with lot’s of IT infrastructure relying on old code – it is not possible to rewrite all the old code in a “container friendly” way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ingress triology</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-12-14-expose-kubernertes-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-12-14-expose-kubernertes-services/</guid>
      <description>Deploying http services in a Kubernetes cluster can be a bit challenging, although the basic principles are simple it is not always easy to manage all the details. Docker &amp;amp; Kubernetes were designed with isolation in mind ( they are called containers for a reason ). You need to understand the Ingress triology properlly : Ingress -&amp;gt; Service -&amp;gt; Containers.
The Container The fist step is to have the container running, inside the container there is a service running that accepts HTTP connections – let’s say tomcat running a webserver.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing Secure Applications</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-11-19-develop-secure-appls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-11-19-develop-secure-appls/</guid>
      <description>Everyday there is a new story about a hacking incident somewhere, developing secure applications is definitely one of the most important challenges in the software world.
A good analogy is the defence of a castle, in the medieval world castles were very important. In a anarchic world with many threads they were the centres of power and stability. But how to defend a castle from your enemy’s ? a well built castle in a high point was a clear advantage, will a relatively small force it could be defended against a much powerful enemy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read last week</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-10-12-read-last-week-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-10-12-read-last-week-3/</guid>
      <description>NotPetya The Untold Story of NotPetya, the Most Devastating Cyberattack in History. Fear At the Open Source Summit, Window Snyder, Chief Security Officer at Intel, explains why fear is not a good motivator for improving cyber-security and provides insight into how to improve software defenses. Security  In today&amp;rsquo;s world, computers are now so omnipresent that there is no longer any such thing as cybersecurity, online security, or computer security – there&amp;rsquo;s only security.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>E-Nightmare</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-08-24-e-nightmare/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-08-24-e-nightmare/</guid>
      <description>“E-Government” has been quite a trendy buzzword all around Europe, according to the UN E-Government survey Portugal ranks 29 in worldwide E-Government services which is not great but not too bad either. For sake of comparison number 1 is Denmark, Belgium is 28 and Poland 33.
Anyway It is cool that many public services have been made available online. I just wonder what the ranking would be if they considered security.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The new normal ?</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-08-17-165/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-08-17-165/</guid>
      <description>Last week, CUF hospital, one of the biggest Portuguese private hospitals was attacked by ransomware, you can read about it here if you can read Portuguese.
seems that the the SamSam ransomware was used, likely by the same grupo that has been targeting hospitals around the globe .
There are not many details available, the Hospital claims that “Everything is normal”, but apparently some exams were lost, likely encrypted by the ransomware, as they refused to pay for the ransom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read last week - Whois GDPR ?</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-04-30-read-last-week-whois-gdpr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-04-30-read-last-week-whois-gdpr/</guid>
      <description>Hey, so Europe&amp;rsquo;s GDPR privacy deadline for Whois? We&amp;rsquo;re going to miss it &amp;hellip; by a year or so https://www.theregister.co.uk/2018/04/10/gdpr_whois_regulations/ China “Social Credit Score” http://newyork.cbslocal.com/2018/04/24/china-assigns-every-citizen-a-social-credit-score-to-identify-who-is-and-isnt-trustworthy/ Google new Chat service https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/google/google-accused-of-showing-total-contempt-for-android-users-privacy/</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read Last Week - Everybody loves Facebook !</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-26-read-last-week-everybody-loves-facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-26-read-last-week-everybody-loves-facebook/</guid>
      <description>The register  Facebook&amp;rsquo;s inflection point: Now everyone knows this greedy mass surveillance operation for what it is  Slashdot This past week, a New Zealand man was looking through the data Facebook had collected from him in an archive he had pulled down from the social networking site. While scanning the information Facebook had stored about his contacts, Dylan McKay discovered something distressing: Facebook also had about two years worth of phone call metadata from his Android phone</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DST and Software</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-26-dst-and-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-26-dst-and-software/</guid>
      <description>Last weekend was a 47 hour oddity; across Europe it is like this every last weekend of March due to the annual DST change to “Summer Hour”. It is annoying but I know if could be worse, at least these changes are unified and regulated, thus all the counties that are part of the EU &amp;ldquo;unified clock regime&amp;rdquo; make the change in the same day.
These changes tend to remind me of years ago when I’ve worked in a software that processed Television audiences, what to do with the GAP when the clock jumps from SAT 1:00 AM to SAT 2:00 AM ?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read last week - Cambridge Analytica</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-20-read-last-week-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-20-read-last-week-2/</guid>
      <description>BBC on Cambridge Analytica
Tech giant Facebook and data analytics firm Cambridge Analytica are at the centre of a dispute over the harvesting and use of personal dat
&amp;nbsp;
BGR on Slingshot
A nation-state developed a piece of malware so powerful that it can steal everything that’s happening on a computer without even being install on the target device itself. Instead, it resides on a router. It’s called Slingshot and it was recently discovered by Kaspersky Labs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read last week - MoviePass</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-12-read-last-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-12-read-last-week/</guid>
      <description>Wow
MoviePass CEO Mitch Lowe told an audience at a Hollywood event last Friday that the app tracks moviegoers&amp;rsquo; locations before and after each show they watch. &amp;ldquo;We get an enormous amount of information,&amp;rdquo;
Hardcoded Password Found in Cisco Software
&amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do I know if a particular Web site is secure ? HTTP vs HTTPs</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-09-how-do-i-know-if-a-particular-web-site-is-secure-part-1-http-vs-https/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-09-how-do-i-know-if-a-particular-web-site-is-secure-part-1-http-vs-https/</guid>
      <description>The short answer is you don’t know … there is no simple ways to check, web infrastructure these days is complex and there is no public reporting of security practices used or even testing reports. The web owner can ( and will if they care about security ) use some kind of vulnerability testing, but it’s actually not nice to test 3rd party sites for vulnerabilities and generally people don’t make these public.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is P@ssword1 more secure than password ?</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-06-is-pssword1-more-secure-than-password/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-06-is-pssword1-more-secure-than-password/</guid>
      <description>On the scope on the GDPR there was some recent news in Portugal regarding Government guidelines for online public services. Atually public service security is an important issue as in Portugal we have lot’s of personal info in public sites, for example a service call eFactura stores basically every invoice where you have put a VAT number – thus very valuable info.
The new guidelines are still under discussion, but a kind of pre-release showed up today in todays specialized press.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read last week</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-05-read-last-wekk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-05-read-last-wekk/</guid>
      <description>The economist on “self driving cars” 
Particularly interesting is this part regarding privacy “AVs will record everything that happens in and around them. When a crime is committed, the police will ask nearby cars if they saw anything. Fleet operators will know a great deal about their riders”.
Wired on China “Big Brother” Social Credits approach
Kind of old news, but found it last week …&amp;ldquo;Imagine a world where many of your daily activities were constantly monitored and evaluated… It&amp;rsquo;s not hard to picture, because most of that already happens….</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Privacy vs Value</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-01-75/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-03-01-75/</guid>
      <description>Data is new Oil, I don’t know who came up with the analogy, I think I’ve read it 1st on Wired but it really highlight’s the value of data these days.
This should be a reminder that data is valuable, likely you wouldn’t consider sending a few bottles of gasoline to BP just because it’s fun but you produce a huge amount of data that you are giving to online companies without getting much in return.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Bitcoin, Cryptocurrencies and Cryptomining</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-02-27-about-bitcoin-cryptocurrencies-and-cryptomining/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-02-27-about-bitcoin-cryptocurrencies-and-cryptomining/</guid>
      <description>The current cryptocurrency trend brings fresh challenges to security, and should be a concern even if you, like me don’t understand where’s the fun of Bitcoin and don’t care much about it.
Cryptocurrencies were one of the greatest trends in 2017, in particular the crypto “star” Bitcoin that started the year around 1000$ and ended it well above 10000$. Although I really don’t find Bitcoin particularly interesting ( just go elsewhere if you are looking for investment tips – I’m not really good at it ) I think that the concept behind it, Blockchain, has potential and can be useful in a lot of different ways.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Spectre &amp; Meltdown</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-02-23-about-spectre-meltdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-02-23-about-spectre-meltdown/</guid>
      <description>For several reasons Meltdown and Spectre are a very interesting set of vulnerabilities that illustrates well the challenges involved to create secure software applications these days.
Details &amp;amp; more info in :
https://meltdownattack.com/
Some semi random thoughts about it :    Although not so risky as been portrayed in the press, basically both vulnerabilities are related to isolation - means that a potential attacker can use them to get information on the local computing device, not to attack remote systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About GDPR</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-02-23-about-gdpr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/posts/2018-02-23-about-gdpr/</guid>
      <description>GDPR is something that is been given some headaches to people like me, involved in secure software development, it stands for “General Data Protection Regulation” ( seehttps://www.eugdpr.org/), it’s a new EU wide regulation coming from the European Parliament that impacts companies that collect or process data related to European Citizens. The GDPR will be enforced after 25 May 2018 and means potential heavy fines for non-complaint companies.
Compliance will cause some concerns as according to the European Commission &amp;ldquo;personal data is any information relating to an individual, whether it relates to his or her private, professional or public life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://jcjramos.github.io/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jcjramos.github.io/contact/</guid>
      <description>I’m not a huge fan of social media, to contact me please use a old fashion email, address jcarlosr[dot here]pt[at here]gmail[and other dot]com. If you really like social media, eventually you can find me on LinkedIn.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>